<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly newe short treatyse instructyng euery parson, howe they shulde trade theyr lyues in ye imytacyon of vertu, and ye shewyng of vyce [et] declaryng also what benefyte man hath receaued by christ, through theiffusyon of hys most precyous blowde.</title>
            <author>Hart, Henry, fl. 1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02757)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 44:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly newe short treatyse instructyng euery parson, howe they shulde trade theyr lyues in ye imytacyon of vertu, and ye shewyng of vyce [et] declaryng also what benefyte man hath receaued by christ, through theiffusyon of hys most precyous blowde.</title>
                  <author>Hart, Henry, fl. 1549.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By me Robert Stoughton. Dwelling within Ludgate, at the sygne of the Byshhoppes Myter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Impri[n]ted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[Anno. 1548. the. 23. October]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Henry harte.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B [C]² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4001:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4001:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Godly Newe ſhort treatyfe inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng euery parſon, howe they ſhulde trade theyr lyues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Imytacyon of Vertu / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhewyng of vyce, &amp; declaryng alſo what benefyte man hath receaued by chriſt, through the effuſyon of hys moſt precyous bloude.</p>
            <p>Impri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted At London by me Robert Stoughton. Dwelling with in Ludgate, at the ſygne of the Byſſhoppes My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4001:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4001:2"/>
            <head>Grace mercye and peace of concience be Multyplyed and encreaced amonge all them that loue oure lorde Ieſus Chryſt (the truthe of God) in purenes of mynd Amen.</head>
            <p>BRetheren beloued in oure Sauy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oure Ieſus Chryſte,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note> Conſyder (I Pray you) the greate good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he hath called you by hys grace to the knowledg of him ſelf / throwghe the worde whyche is greate mercye towarde you in Chryſte Ieſu. for fleaſhe and bloude (ſayth. Sayncte paule) can not enherite the kyngdome of i God / neyther can Corrupcyon inheryte pncorrupcyon. Nichodemus beynge A aharyſey and a man lerned, Ye knowe, dfter the iudgementes of men, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wued alſo with the gyftes of nature / as wytte, reſon, knoledge and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding naturall: yet coulde not he of hys owne powre and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth comprehend the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly doctryne of oure Saueour chriſt, nor perceyue the celeſtyal mynde therof
<pb facs="tcp:4001:3"/>
tyll he was holpen by grace from God aboue, and borne a new, Not of mortall ſede / but of immortall, whyche, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth &amp; laſteth for euer.<note place="margin">Ihon. iii.</note> For that whych is born of the fleſhe is fleſhe (ſaith chriſt) But that whych is borne of the ſpyryte is ſpryte. Therfore ſayde Chryſte Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte thou be borne of water, and of the holy ſpiryte, thou canſt not ſe the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. For al thought god ſynce the begynnynge hath appropryated cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne gyftes of grace to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by reaſon wherof he dothe excell in hys creacyon, all other creatures not only in ſhape of body, ſtatute and contenaunce alſo in the aforſayde ſpyrytuall gyftes of grace annexed to nature as wytt rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, knoledge and vnderſtandynge. for when god made man at the begynnyng he gaue hym a Reaſonable ſoule, from the whych procedeth ſo God withdraw it not a mynde of vnderſtandynge in all mankynde, aboue all other creaturs w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the lorde hathe created vpon the face of the whole earthe: yet trulye withoute the eſpecyall grace of the lord GOD,
<pb facs="tcp:4001:3"/>
and gyfte from heauen aboue (although a man he neuer ſo wyſe and excellente) Yet can he not obtaygne of hys owne ſtrenght (whych commethe, of oure firſt byrthe) the trewe knowledge, feare and loue of god, which fell from vs in adam</p>
            <p>But by grace are ye ſaued through faythe / (ſayth paule) and not of youre ſelfes nor throught workes,<note place="margin">Roma. iii.</note> leaſte any man ſhuld boaſt hymſelfe: but by chryſt are we ſaued and made the beloued ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the hygheſtt: As Wytneſſe the ſayncte Iohn ſayinge: He gaue them power to be the Sonnes of GOD, as many as beleue in hys name whych are not born of fleaſhe nor of bloud, nor of the wyll of man / but of GOD.<note place="margin">Iohan. i. Roma. viij</note> And through hym (my bretherne) ye haue obtayned not only knowledge and Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gemente to dyſcerne and iudge betwyxt the good &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euyl: but alſo ye are made able through the ſpyryte whyche a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in you whyche ye haue of God to choſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good &amp; to leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euyll.<note place="margin">Galla. <hi>4.</hi> a i. Cor. ij. b</note> for the lord no doubte, is a ſpirite, ſayth paule and wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord is, ther is lybertye
<pb facs="tcp:4001:4"/>
and throughe hym ye are made ſtronge / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye obey,<note place="margin">ij. Cor. iij.</note> for through Chryſte (ſaith he) I can doo al thyngs, whych he hath made me able. Bretheren, yf ye obeye &amp; be now ſedde by the holy ſpyrit of God,<note place="margin">Roma vjij</note> then trulye are ye made the fre ſonnes of God, then ſhal ye alſo be made perfet and obteyne vyctory agaynſt ſyn, death and hell, whych is the whole power of Sathan our mortall ennemye. Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, deceaue not your ſelues / for loke to whome ye do obey / truly hys ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ye are, to whome ye doo obeye, whether it be by obedience vnto rightuouſnes or ſynne vnto death. In Adam trulye we were all deade / but in Chryſte we are al made alyue, as manye as beleue in hys name as perteynyng to the fleſh (as. ſ. Paule ſayth we wer all naturally born y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren of wrath,<note place="margin">Roma vi.</note> as wel as al other becauſe of orygynall Synne, that reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in all fleſhe.</p>
            <p>Reaſon was blynd and nature cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte, therfore coulde it not obeye to the wyll of GOD / but vyolentlye ſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue agaynſte hym / deſyrynge that he ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:4001:4"/>
and hatyng that he loued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">i. Corin. iij</note> For the naturall manne (ſayth Saynct Paul) perceyueth not the thynges of Goode / that belonge to the ſpyryte,<note place="margin">i. Corin. iij.</note> for they are but folyſhnes vnto hym.</p>
            <p>Neyther can he perceue them (ſayth he) for they are Spyrytuallye examyned: but he that is ſpyrytuall, dyſcuſſeth all thynges.</p>
            <p>Brethern, youre mindes are now light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by grace, and ye haue now receyued the ſpyryte of God / whych bryngethe. knowledge and a perfecte willinge obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyent mynde to do the wyll of God:</p>
            <p>But whoſoeuer hath not the Spyryte, the ſame is none of hys.</p>
            <p>For aſmuche as ye are partakers of the holy ſpyryte, and are borne a new, yeare not now (my bretherne) vnder the lawe but vnder grace.</p>
            <p>Obey vnto the fourme of doctryne (I praye you) wherunto ye are called. for trulye God hathe pleaſure in a louelye harte. And an obedyente Mynde is all wayes at peace wyth hym.</p>
            <p>The naturall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not renued, knoweth
<pb facs="tcp:4001:5"/>
not God / neyther is he obedyente to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteowſenes, which is of value be for hym, neyther can be / ſayethe paule / For delectacyon and coſtome in euyll / blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth there vnderſtandinge that they are not obedyente / no not to that goodnes that naturall reaſone teacheth them / &amp; they ſaye they know God, loue hym and kepe all hys commaundementes. They deceyue themſelues vtterlye thynkynge them ryche, when the world fauoureth them, when indede they are blynde and poore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for though they poſſeſſe muche yet indeyd they haue no thynge. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for the hope of the vngodly is as the dry thyſtle flower.<note place="margin">Luke. xij.</note> For theyre faythe is vayne and of none effecte. When they heare the woorde of God, whiche is the trwth they are not obedyente to do ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they delyghte in euyll / and haue no deſyre, to folowe ryghteouſnes ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore / when they come to the knowledge of the ſcrypture they fall ſodenlye into many daungerous erroures. Some be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they Wolde be hydde from Gods wynde them ſelfes in a folyſhe cloke of
<pb facs="tcp:4001:5"/>
myar neceſſyty / ſayng in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if can not otherwyſe be: When in dede they ſtryue not at all to make reſyſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but doo lette the fleſhelye mynde runne whether it luſteth, So for lacke of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence they fall into wyllfull ſynne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauyng them ſelfes in their owne yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. To do yuell thei haue power becauſe they wyll / but to doo well they haue none at al, for they wyl not. Thus the vngodly abyde ſtyll in theyre owne luſtes, and wyll not leaue of. But as Sayncte paule ſaythe they heape toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the treaſure of wrathe agaynſt the daye of vengeaunce: when ſhalbe ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the righteous Iudgemente of God w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> wil reward eueri ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / acording to his dedes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / prayſe, honour / &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mortalytye to them whych contynue in good doing and ſeke eternall lyfe.</p>
            <p>But vnto them that are rebellyous / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doo dyſobeye the truethe and followe Inyquytye / ſhall come Indygnatyon / Wrathe / Trybulatyon / and anguyſſhe vppon the Soule of euerye manne that dothe euell / forwyth GOD trulye / the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:4001:6"/>
is no Reſpecte of Parſonnes / for he wyll rewarde euerye manne after their dedes.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles the multytude of the vngodlye wyll not repente, for they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue pleaſure to lyue in Synne, and ſome that were eſcaped from the fylthines of the woorlde (as Saynte Peter ſayth) through the knowledge of the Lorde,<note place="margin">ij. Petr. ij.</note> and of the Sauyoure and Redeamer IESVS CHRISTE are yet entangled agayne therin and are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
            <p>Soo is the latter ende woorſe then the begynnynge. For of whome a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne is ouercome, to the ſame he is in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <p>Therfore theyr myndes are vnſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and are to fled to and froo, as a ſhyp in the ſea, wyth ragynge wyndes wyth euerye perſwaſyon and blaſte that com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth.</p>
            <p>Some haue erred / and (as Sayncte paul ſayth) are turned to vayne iangli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (as yf they thoughte the holy Relygyon of Chryſte oure ſauyoure and Redea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:4001:6"/>
to ſtand in ſpeakyng &amp; hearynge o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nly, and not rather in obeyng to the wyl of the Lorde GOD to do the ſame (by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they wold be teachers) in the moſt holy ſcrypture. And (as Paule ſayth) vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng not what they ſpeak,<note place="margin">j Tymo. j.</note> nor wherof they affyrme.</p>
            <p>But the Lorde God hath called you dearelye beloued by hys Grace, that ye ſhulde obeye to the truethe, and be lyke faſſhyoned to hys ſonne.</p>
            <p>Caſte not awaye your confydence whyche hath ſo great reward to recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence / for trulye to be in oure ſauyoure Chryſte is to be a newe Creature.</p>
            <p>A wyllynge mynd maketh an obedyent harte and a dylygent hande: Therfore as the holye Prophet, ſayeth plowe vp your freſſhe ground lyke dylygent huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen / and ſow no more amongeſt the thornes: So ſhall ye brynge forthe the frutes of ryghtuouſnes, and reape the rewarde of wel doyng, the huſband man laboureth the grounde dylygentlye in due ſeaſon, as ye knowe, that the lord maye proſpere the worke of hys hands</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4001:7"/>Conſyder your tyme lykwyſe and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe not the grace of God whyles it ys offred you,<note place="margin">Math. xv. Hebre. xij.</note> leaſt at another tyme when ye wolde gladdelye ye be not heard, for as muche as yeare called by grace to be chylderen of lyght / and heyres of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal lyfe, for ye haue receyued of hys ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpyrite in earneſte of your ſaluacyon in that ye haue conſented already wyth youre whoale hartes to the Truthe of God.</p>
            <p>I beſeche you by the mercyfulnes of God, obey to the forme of doctryn, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>revnto ye are called.<note place="margin">Roma. xiij</note> And facyon not youre ſelues lyke vnto thys Woorlde. but beye chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged / &amp; as ſaynt paul ſayth in youre ſhape by the renuynge of your Wyttes / that ye maye fele what that good &amp; acceptable wyl of god is. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it is wrytten:<note place="margin">Pſal. xciiij</note> To daye yf yow heare hys voyce / harden not your har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for trulye dyſobedyence is hateful, yea and often tymes doth the lorde pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſh it.<note place="margin">Nume. xiij i. Reg. xv. ij. Re. xvij.</note> What was ſayd to kyng Saul by Samuell the prophet / whan he dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed the lordes commaundement, ye
<pb facs="tcp:4001:7"/>
know / hath the Lord (ſayd he) as great pleaſure in brent ſacryfyces and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynges as when the voyce of the Lord is obeyed? Behold ſayd Samuell, to o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beye is better then ſacryfyce, &amp; to harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fatte of ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellyon or dyſobedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is as the ſyn of wytchcraft, &amp; ſtoubburnes as the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of ydolatrye &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For an obedyente harte truly is muche accepted wyth God, and a lowely trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſpryte wyl he not deſpyce, it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry pleſaunt grounde prepared a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d made ready (as it were by the Induſtrye and laboure of a dylygent huſband man) for the lorde to plante all vertu and grace in. Brethern / obey to the wyll of God and ſhewe a wyllynge mynde. By your deydes be no lenger ſlouthefull, nether ouer muche afrayed / neyther to haſtye wythowte meaſure, wantynge dyſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. But kepe meaſure in all youre wayes: and wyſely conſyder place and time, for ye are now no more your own, but are dearelye bought wythe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte precyous bloude of Ieſu. Yf the lorde
<pb facs="tcp:4001:8"/>
fynde you faythfull in lytle, know for a ſuertye,<note place="margin">Eccle. j.</note> that he wyll make you rulers ouer much.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Peter. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Therfor (as Saynct peter ſaythe) in your faythe mynyſter vertue in vertue knowledge in knowledge, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perauncye intemperauncye, pacyence, in pacynece / godlynes in godlynes, brother lye kyndnes in brotherlye kindnes, loue &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Remembre the mater is wayghty, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for be not deceyued. Surely yf ye wyll walke by thys rule, ye can not fall, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſhall ye be ledde a wronge way. Go not from the worde of God, declyne ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght hand neyther to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> left / leafte ye peryſſſhe from the ryghte way, for as the braunche can beare no fruyte of hym ſelfe excepte he abyde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vyne (ſayth chryſte) no more can ye excepte yea byde in me.<note place="margin">Iohn. xv.</note> Se that your faythe be lyuely cleauynge ſuer to the holy word of god, which is already grafted in you Trewlye (except you haue beleued in vayne) it is of powre to ſaue your ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, for it is quyck and myghty in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyon, &amp; ſharper / then any two edged
<pb facs="tcp:4001:8"/>
ſword<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye knowe brethern / the ende of the commaundements, is loue that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of a puer hart, of a good conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and of fayth vnfayned: whoſe fruts can not be hydde. But as for ſuche as turne backe vnto ther own wyckednes the lorde ſhall lead them furth with the eueldoers / but peace ſhalbe vppon Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell. Truly knowledge is daungerous / where loue and obedyence is lackynge / for it tyckelyth the mynde of foles, and lefteth them vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vanyty: But ſuch as ſeke to encreaſe in vertu walke ſurely. Therfore ſearche not vnreuerently the ſacred worde of god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leaſt ye ſtumbel in your way / and take aſodeyn fal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge is a gyfte of the ſpryte, and in the hand of god a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he meaſureth hys gyfts to hys creatures at hys owne pleaſure and wyll, Therfor, whether ye obtayne at hys hand ether much or lytyll, praiſe him for it / and be concent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his doyng. Search not the gronde of ſuch thinges / (ſayth the wyſe man) as are to myghty for the: But loke what god commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and thynke apon that alwayes: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:4001:9"/>
be not curyous in many of hys works for he that louethe pereyll ſhall peryſhe therin. Grudge not agaynſte the good manne of the houſe / though he do wyth hys owne as he leyſt, leaſte thou be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouyd and ſent awaie with rebuke.</p>
            <p>Be ye therfor dyſcret and ſobre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſettell youre Hartes in the true feare of God, and arme youre ſoules to temptacyon. Turne your eares to the truth, my bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theren, and vſe the gyftes that ye haue receaued wyth a lowly a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d an obedyent harte faythfully / that your frutes maye appeare and receue not the grace of god in vayn, for it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I haue hard the in a tyme accepted, and in the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uatyon haue I ſuccoured the.<note place="margin">ij. Cor. v.</note> Beholde now in that well accepted tyme / ſayth paule / now is the day of health / lett vs geue none occaſyon of euyll / that in our mynyſtryng, or offyce ther be found no faulte, But in al thynges / let vs behaue oure ſelfes / as mynyſters of God: In much pacyence / in afflycyons, in neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, in a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guyſſhes / in ſtryfes / in labours in watchynges, in faſtynges / and in pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>renes.
<pb facs="tcp:4001:9"/>
&amp;c. many do heare rede &amp; ſpeak the holye ſcryptures, (prayſed be God) and many deſyre to know muche. But bleſſed and happye are ye, whych obeye to the truthe / So that ye doo therafter for the kyngdome of God, ſtandeth not in words (as ye wel know) but in powr &amp; workynge the wycked ſynners haue God, and hys holy worde many tymes in their mouthes: but they walke ſtyll in ther oun corrupt ways<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> truly they are the bounde ſeruaunts of ſynne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dued to luſtes &amp; ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne.<note place="margin">ij. Pet. iij.</note> For of whome a manne is ouercomed Saythe Sayncte peter to the ſame he is in bon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage. The vngodly manne hath not the feare of God, before hys eyes: Nether doth he regarde the law of the hygheſt. Therfore ſhall he not be preſerued, for God regardeth hym not, neyther wyll he defend him i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme of trouble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can ſuche proſper / as take parte agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hygheſt, &amp; prouok y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde to anger,<note place="margin">Apoca. xix</note> conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther vnlawful dedes? &amp; fyght ageynſt the holy ſpryte of our God: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet they ſay in ther hartes Tuſhe, God
<pb facs="tcp:4001:10"/>
ſeeth it not, the God of Iacob regardeth it not they do euell / and they ſay they do wel ye althogh they know / mary tymes the contrary becauſe they delyte in euell theyr folyſh hartes are blynded. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt they reape the frutes of theyre labours when they thynke them ſelues wyſe they become foles, bycauſe theyr vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng is blynded. When they think they knowe God loue hym,<note place="margin">An ydoll is that whych hathe the loue of the harte and is placed in the towme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureis ther w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> he l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth beſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> and ſerue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt truly they ſerue an ydoll and a falſe God / in hys ſteade and place / fayned of theyr own fleſhly luſtes and carnall affec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyons and of the eternal God ſaue the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me onely) they knowe nothing / for where a mans treaſure is, ſayth Chryſte / there wyll hys harte be alſo. In wordes truly many ſay they know god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but wyth their dedes they ſhamfullye deny him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in that they refuſe to lyue accordyng to hys com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundements &amp; wyl they haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuely teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god made in the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous bloude and death of our ſauyoure Chryſte Ieſu / to all that beleue in hym / (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay) whych wyth a free harte, do put themſelues vnder the couenaunt of God to do hys wyll. And after theyr ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:4001:10"/>
Imagynacyon fayne themſelues an other waye to the kyngdome of heauen / as eaſy and broade to the fleſſhe as they luſt: they refuſed the narrowe waye,<note place="margin">Thys way is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, and ſtrayte / to the fleaſhe / but breade and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye to a wyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g mynde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſtrayght gate that leadeth vnto lyfe and haue choſen that broode eaſy waye to ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue after theyre luſtes whych leadeth al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walke in it, into euerlaſtynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon on wyſely do they forſake the word of the lord whyche he ordeyned a lantern and a ſure lyghte vnto theyr fete / to walk in extreme darknes, of theyr owne blynd Imagynacyons neuertheles, thus ſayth the lord our mercyfull God / vnto the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly ſynners.<note place="margin">Eze. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> If I ſaye to the wycked he ſhall dye ſayth the lorde yet yf he tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne from his wyckednes and do the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is equall and ryght he ſhall ſurelye lyue, &amp; not dye &amp; again, O / turnt you tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne you ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord / O why wyl ye dye? As truly as I lyue, ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, I haue no pleaſuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the death of a ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner but wyl rather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert &amp; lyue. &amp;c. Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / I beſeche you for the dere mercy of God, eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teme your ſaluatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and health w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous &amp; is now ſo frely offred vnto you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cious bloud of Ieſu: haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4001:11"/>
youre owne ſoules, and ſhewe loue and charyte to the poure opreſſed / the lame blynde and nedye loke vpon your ſelfes wyth an inwarde eye / and ſee that your ſoules be refreaſhed, that they may liue O / why wyll ye dye, conuerte and turne to the lorde, wyth youre whole hartes / from your wycked and ſynfull wayes, &amp; trulye your ſynnes are forgeuen you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whye eſteme ye ſo much the vayne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of thys worlde? Whych are the delyghtes of the carnall and earthelye mynd ſeyng they are ſo vayne and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytorye. Remember Eſau: Sell not your enheretaunce whyche is precyous for ſoo vyle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a pryce / leaſte after when ye wolde gladlye obtayne, ye be put by. Bretheren, Conſyder ye are not nowe vnder the law / but vnder grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe ye are grafte / into Ieſuchryſte by faith O, therfore I beſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h you / doo no more wyllfully euyll: Soo can fynne nowe doo ye no harme. My lytell chyldryne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yt I vnto you ſaythe Saynct Iohn that ye ſynne not. But if any man ſynne: yet haue we an Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb facs="tcp:4001:11"/>
with the father (ſayth he) Ieſus chriſt whych is ryghtuous. &amp;c. For the lord ordereth a good mans goyng (ſayth ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye Dauyd) and hathe pleaſure in hys waye. Though he fail, he ſhall not be hurt, for the lord vpholdeth hym,<note place="margin">Allthough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rightous happen to fall ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme into ſynne: yet they haue an aduoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te for it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father, bicauſe thei wolde not ſynne. Pſa. <hi>36</hi> and <hi>.90</hi>
               </note> with hys hande. &amp;c. O, that ye wolde nowe obeye to the voyce of God, conteyned in hys ſacred word, that ye myght receyue Chryſte into your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Bretheren beloued in our ſauyour Chryſt Ieſu, I beſech you for the dear loue of Chryſt Ieſu (whyche refuſed not to ſuffer reproue of the worldde, &amp; to geue hys lyfe for oure ſakes that we might lyue by hym) be warned in time leaſte Sathan beguyle you, and brynge you a ſlepe wyth the world through in ordynate deſyre of vayne ryches, ſory a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pleaſur therof, couetyng after mery and ioyfull dayes here relyghtyng the mynd in wantonnes or worldly luſts, whych is the playne waye to vtter deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tructyon. Know ye not, how the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſeketh buſuly by theſe thynges to betray you? And how he layeth carnal
<pb facs="tcp:4001:12"/>
fleaſhelye and worldlye pleaſures as a bayte, wherin venym / yeth hydde before your eyes to catche your myndes / that he may ſo carrye you awaye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For as the fowlers bayt betrayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fowles. Soo doth the vayne pleaſures of thys world begylde the myndes of fowles: For through the deſyre of it the enemy ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leadynge the ſynner from one vanytye to an other tyll he haue ſo broughte hym in woofull bondage, and moſte myſerable captyuytye. But thys ye knowe my brethern. I meane the ſea ſone, how it is tyme (as Sayncte paule ſayth) that we ſhulde nowe a wake owt of ſlepe,<note place="margin">Rom. xiii.</note> for nowe is oure ſaluacyon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, then when we beleued. The nyghte is paſte, and the day is come nygh. Lett vs therfore Caſte a waye the dedes of darekenes, and put on the Armoure of lyghte. Lett vs nowe walke honeſtelye (ſaythe he) as in the daye lyghte: not in eatynge and drynkynge, chambrynge, &amp; wantones nether in ſtrife &amp; enuyeng but put ye on the lord Ieſus Chryſt, &amp; make not prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh to fulfyll the luſtes of it. Truly we are called (as
<pb facs="tcp:4001:12"/>
ye know to ſuffer wyth Chryſt, that we myght be made partakers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym in glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry for yf we were grafted lyke hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in death Then ſhall we be lyke hym alſo in the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrectyon,<note place="margin">Ieſus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dixit illis. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dico, vobis quod vos qui ſequuti eſtis me, in regeneraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one cum ſederit fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis in ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e maieſtatis fue. &amp;c Math. xix</note> the rych man lyueth here in al pleaſures and fared delycyouſly. And Lazarus lyued in trouble a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d payne. But after this lyfe Lazarus receued ioye ſaith Chryſte and the rych man payne for A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braham ſayde vnto hym: ſonne remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre that thou in thy lyfe tyme receyuedſt thy good and contrary wiſe Lazarus pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, now therfore is he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art punyſſhed. Our ſauiour, Chryſte trulye being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord of our glory (during y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time of thys lyfe (walked here through many trybulacyons. He refuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcepter and crown of a worldly kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayn fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhyp &amp; glory y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the world could geue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; receued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mourni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g deares on hys head a crowne of ſharpe thornes &amp; a rede for a ſceptre in his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Mat xxvi</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might ſo for our ſakes aco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of his heuenly father, &amp; gette vyctory againſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole powre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy. Chryſt ſuffred for vs ſayth. ſ. peter leauy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld follow hys fotſteppes / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> dyd
<pb facs="tcp:4001:13"/>
no ſynne / neyther was ther guyle found in his mouthe. &amp;c. Chryſte had no fely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cytye in thys preſente worlde whych is now corrupte, but hys reioyſyng was in the wylle of hys father, and he had a great reſpecte to the rewarde at the end Yf the ſonne of God takyng oure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon hym, myghte not eſcape / but muſte drynke of thys Cuppe, who ſaied The ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te is not aboue the maſter, neyther the meſſynger greater then he that ſendethe hym. Thynke not ye to eſcape / my Brethern, yf ye intende to be made partakers with hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his fathers heauenlye kyngdome. Therfore wyth pacyence poſſeſſe your ſowles, and lyke faytheful Sowldiours of Ieſus chriſt, take vp youre Croſſe / and folowe hym, for trulye he hathe promyſed, that yf ye be partakers with hym in ſufferyng / ye ſhall be partakers wyth hym in glorye. But yf you lyue after the fleaſh &amp; haue your pleaſure amongeſt the wycked: ye muſt dye: But if ye mortify the dedes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh / throughe the ſpyryte, then ſhall ye lyue. Brethern / ye are called of God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4001:13"/>
ye ſhuld be holy. Therfor I wolde not that ye ſhulde now be partakers in the dedes of the wycked,<note place="margin">i. Corin. x.</note> and haue fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe wyth deuels, for truly (as ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t paul ſayth) ye can not be partakers of the lordes table, and of the table of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, neyther drynke of the lordes cup and of the cup of deuels, Eyther ſhall we prouoke the lorde (ſaythe he) or are we ſtronger then he? ye can not ſerue God and mammon, how agreeth light wyth darkenes? ryghtouſnes wyth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryghtouſnes? or Chryſt wyth Belyaſ? The hart that goeth two ways truly is hated, and ſuch as are dobble tounged / are accurſed of God.</p>
            <p>What can it proffite a man to wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne all the world / wyth the loſſe and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage of hys owne ſowle? yea what ſhal he geue to redeme it agayn with al he that ſeketh to ſaue hys lyfe ſhall loſe it (ſaythe chryſte): But he that wyl loſe hys lyfe for my ſake, ſhal ſaue it. yea bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed and happye are thoſe, (Sayth the ſpyryte) that loue not ther lyues vnto the deathe: Truly they ſhall receaue a
<pb facs="tcp:4001:14"/>
Crowne of life. And although ye know the truth already (my Brethere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dearely beloued in our Sauioure Ieſu chryſte yet I thynke it not vayne by theſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / to ſtyrre vpp your remembraunce for trulye it is my dylyee that ye ſhulde not peryſhe wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. but that ye ſhulde turne from your ſynnes, and liue Therfore / ſeynge God hath called you wyth an holye callynge, for he hath ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed your harts with the oyle of grace &amp; opened your vnderſtandynge, by hys holy ſpyryte: Soo that ye haue nowe ſene hys holy wyll declared vnto vs in Chryſte Ieſu And haue conſented, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the truthe of God I beſeche you by the mercyfullnes of God / make your bodyes, a quycke and lyuelye ſacryfyce / holy &amp; acceptable to God / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> as ſayncte Paule ſayth is your reſonable ſeruynge of God, And faſcyon not youre ſelues lyke vnto thys woorlde, but be ye chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in youre ſhappe by the Renuynge of youre wyttes. Seynge ye are nowe ryſen wyth Chryſte, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te youre myndes aboue on heauenly thynges where Chriſt ſyttethe on the ryghte hande of God the
<pb facs="tcp:4001:14"/>
father and not on the thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> art on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. Brethern deceue not your ſelues brynge furthe the perfecte frutes belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge to repentan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / which is amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of lyfe. Let it appere I praye you that yeare of chryſte / &amp; haue harde the woorde in dede. Trulye it is good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the harte be eſtabliſſhed with grace and not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo vanyces, Yf vertu encreſe, ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be yole, nor yet vnfruteful i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of chryſte. But he that wanteth thys / as ſaynte Peter ſayth, is blyndes gropynge for the way w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> hys hand and hath forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his olde ſynnes for true fayth is lyuely / &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be hydde neyther may ſhe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any wiſe dwell or abide alone for ſhe hath a great deſyre to many vertues. She acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye the her ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gods wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; loue She is nouryſhed daylye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bryght ſonne of ryghteouſnes / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth her plantes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwete ſhowres of grace. Through perfecte obedyence to the wall of god, ſhe ſpredeth furthe her brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches in due ſeaſon whereby ſhe obtayneth a ſuer hope her fruyctes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeade from the tree of lyfe / For trulye
<pb facs="tcp:4001:15"/>
truly they are the workes of the ſpirite of God, as loue, ioye / peace, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntelnes, goodnes / faythefullnes meknes / temperancy. for hee eye wayteh vnto the commaundementes of the lord to kepe them: for in the mis her lyfe, Dearly beloued ye are called and choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are waſhed from an euyll concyence: ye are ſanctyfyed by the bloude of Ieſu, through the eternalle ſpyryte / whyche dwelleth in you: By whom / ye are able throught chryſte. whych (as ſaynct pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ſayeth hath made vs able to be myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the new teſtamente. Therfore worke owe your ſaluacion, And (as the Apoſtle peter ſayth) make your callynge and electyon ſuer / through good works. Mortyfye therfore youre membres w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> are earthly. And walke not from henſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourth / as other hethen people walke in vanytye of theyre myndes, blynded in theyr vnderſtandyng / beyng ſtraungers from the lyfe that is in God / throwghe the yngnoraunce that is in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe of the blyndnes of there hartes / whych beynge paſte repentaunce, Haue geuen
<pb facs="tcp:4001:15"/>
themſelues vnto wantonnes, to worke almaner of vncleannes / euen wyth g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> dynes. But ye haue not ſo lerned Chryſte as ſayncte paule ſaythe. yf ſo be ye haue hard of hym and are tawght of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Euen as the truth is in Ieſus ſo then as concernynge the conuerſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tymes paſte, laye from you the olde man whyche is corrupt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (through deceauea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble luſtes, and be ye renued in the ſpyrite of your vnderſtandynge myndes: And put on that newe man whych is ſhapen after the ymag of god, in ryghteouſnes and trew holynes, nowe therfore as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte of God holy and beloued, put on te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der mercy ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dnes hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blenes of mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes, Longe ſufferynge, forbering one another / and forgeuyng one another.<note place="margin">Colloſſ. iij<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> yf anye man haue a quarell to an other (ſaythe Sayncte paule) euen as Chryſt forgaue you, euen ſo do ye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye are called to be chyldren of lyhgt that ye ſhulde be holy and wyth owte blame. yf ye put to a wyllyng mynde ye ſhall fynd the lorde read ye wyth hys grace at youre hande. for God loueth you and therfor wyll be
<pb facs="tcp:4001:16"/>
all wayes defende you and delyuer you in the howle of temptacyon (whych as Chryſte ſaythe ſhall come to tempte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſytt vpon the face of the earth. But ye haue not receyued the ſpyryte of the world, that your felycytye ſhulde be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynges therof: Neyther that ye ſeke God all way owtewardely, and to ſerue hym in the letter. But ye haue receyued the ſpyryte of God, whyche lowſed in your hartes the woorkes of ſynne, and opened the inwarde eyes of your mynd that ye ſhulde nowe haue no more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayle is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away for your hartes / and yeare turned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde that ye maye nowe ſee the bryghte face of God / whyche is hys loue, and mercyfull wyll towardes vs in Chryſte Ieſu. Therfore truly we are called and taughte of God / to ſerue hym in a new conuerſacyon, in ſpyryte and verytye and not in the olde conuerſacyon of the letter. For the letter kylleth (ſayth ſainct paule). But the ſpyryte geueth lyfe. Yf the fyrſte teſtament had bene fauteleſſe ſaythe he,<note place="margin">Hebr. viij / </note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld there no place haue
<pb facs="tcp:4001:16"/>
bene ſoughte for the ſecond. For in rebu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng them he ſayth, Beholde the dayes wyll come (ſayth the Lorde) and I wyll fynyſhe vppon the houſe of Iſraell and vpon the houſe of Iuda a new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not lyke the teſtament that I made with theyr fathers at that tyme when I toke them by the hande and ledde them out of the lande of Egypte for they contynued not in my teſtement and I regarded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſayeth the lorde, But thys is the teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament and I regarded them not ſaythe the lord / But thys is the teſtamente, that I wyll make wyth the houſe of Iſraell After thoſe daies (ſayth the lorde) I wil put milawes in their mindes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in theyr harts I wil wryte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; I wyl be their God, &amp; they ſhall be my people. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord hath now ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> trulye he wryteth hys lawe by hys ſpyryte in theyr hartes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye doo it accordyng to hys wyll. Saincte Paule teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> xv.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus chriſt was a myniſter of the cyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of God, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrme the promeſſes made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led &amp; made miniſters i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / 
<pb facs="tcp:4001:17"/>
and pertakers of the true circumſyſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is inſpryt &amp; not in letter / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye might receue of hys holynes through the ſprit that he hath geuen vs. Therfore (my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) be ye holy, be ye holy in al your conuerſatyon, for it is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Be ye ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for I am holy / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſurely, the things that ye haue in hand be very holy / kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we ye not how that ye ar partakers of the nature of God, by partycipacyon of hys holy ſpyryte whych ye haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? And how that ye are made the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of God, becauſe hys holy ſpryt dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth in you defile not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this holy place leaſt the lord be angry; and ſo ye peryſh from the ryght way. Thys holy cytye new Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Apoca. xxi.</note> Ihon ſawe com down from God out of heauen prepared as a bryde garnyſſhed for her huſbande. And he harde a great voyce out of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen ſaying, Beholde the tabernacle of God is with men, and he wyll dwelle wyth them. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thys holy tabernacle a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d dwelling houſe / hath god pyght among you / and not man, after whyche moyſes was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded
<pb facs="tcp:4001:17"/>
to make all the worke whych wece but ſhadowes (ſayth ſaint Paul) of true thynges to come: And were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned vntyll the tyme of reformacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath God now in thys laſte tyme by Chryſt opened vnto vs, for by hys blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de haue we an open waye in into the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly place, and mooſt holye by the newe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lyuing way, whych he hath prepared for vs though the vayle, that is to ſaye / by hys fleſhe. And by Chryſte are ye belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and made mynyſters in the newe teſtamente and pryeſtes vnto the hygh god to offer in the holy place in holy veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſels of pure golde that acceptable ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce of prayſe and thankeſgeuyng,<note place="margin">Veſſels of pure golde are the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcyences of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purged from the fylthe of ſynne, and Corrupcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> that is to ſaye, the frutes of thoſe lyppes / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do confeſſe hys mooſte holy name / atten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de therfore to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing, that ye haue now harde (my deare bretheren) and as dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re chylderen, labour earneſtly by the hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe of the ſpyryt to kepe your ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpotted of the worlde, that ye may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued and be made the parfecte ſonnes of God / and coheyres wyth our ſauyoure Ieſus Chryſte of hys euerlaſtyng hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb facs="tcp:4001:18"/>
kyngdome. Amen.</p>
            <p>The god of all patience and conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue to eueryone of you grace ſo to labo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and trauayle in youre callynge after the example of Chryſte / that your gyfte maye encreaſe, leaſt you alſo be plucked away in the erourre of the wycked, and fall from your ſtedfaſtnes / But growe in grace and the lorde wyll delyuer you from all euell doyng, and kepe you to hys heauenly kyngdome: to whom be all prayſe / honour and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>The grace of God be wyth your ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t. Amen</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as charytye byndeth me / Henry harte.</signed>
Geue all the prayſe to God, and be alwayes thankfull vnto hym. <dateline>
                  <date>Anno. <hi>1548.</hi> the <hi>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> October</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4001:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
